(upbeat music)
- [Instructor] We will now
discuss typical utility functions
and we will start with something
that we call perfect substitutes, okay?
Typical utility functions
will be utility functions
that we will use in many examples
and have some special
properties and there will be
between I think three and
five of the main ones.
And please beware of the mathematical,
as well as the conceptual
features of this function.
So the first one, as we were saying,
the first utility or
typical utility function
or common utility function will
be the perfect substitutes.
That takes mainly, but not only,
but mainly this kind of
utility specification.
Alpha times x1 plus beta times x2
where alpha and beta will be positive.
So these functions,
however, can take, you know,
depending on alpha and
beta can take many shapes.
If alpha and beta are both equal to one,
this perfect substitutes function
will become simply x1 plus x2.
Okay?
Utility equals x1 plus x2.
As we were saying,
perfect substitutes
utility take the shape.
And an example of it
can be utility equals x1 plus x2.
This is in a sense the simplest example.
How can we find the indifference curves
for this particular utility function?
Well, we can apply the steps
we have found before to draw it
and we will do that here.
We will draw indifference,
so the commodity space here.
And we will do the steps here.
So the first step is to identify
it through the function.
The second one is to set
it equals to one value
on a specific value of
utility that we were, again,
instead of just using some value k,
we're going to directly
say utility level five
and then solving for x2
from that equation.
So when utility level is five,
this is the indifference curve
for that level of utility.
If utility level was 10, we will find
and you can check this,
we will find an indifference
curve that will look like this.
But notice that these utility
functions here and here,
sorry, the indifference
curves here and here
are linear and they are downwards sloped.
That is, they will be something like this.
This could be indifference
curve for utility level 10.
curve for utility level five.
Let us now talk about another,
a second typical utility function.
And in this case, we're going to deal
with what we call perfect complements.
Perfect complements are
utility or are given
by utility functions
that usually, not only,
but usually take this shape
as it's been depicted here.
The bracket, the curly brackets, min,
represents a minimum
function which yes, assigns
as a value of this function
the minimum entry of whatever
is inside the min curly brackets.
Okay, so for example,
if you have the minimum
between three and five, it
will be equal to three simply
because three is indeed the
minimum between three and five.
The simplest perfect complements
will take the shape, the
minimum of x1 and x2.
But a more general
function will be this one,
x1 divided by alpha, x2 divided by beta
with alpha and beta greater than one.
Okay, so let's also go to the iPad
and see how to draw this.
Perfect complements.
Okay, perfect complements.
And the general utility function
for perfect complements
will be the min function
of x1 divided by alpha x2 divided by beta.
But we're going to use, in our example,
a simple version of it,
which is going to be simply the min,
the min
between x1 and x2.
Okay?
So for this utility function,
the indifference curves are actually drawn
in a different way because
it's not straightforward
to draw, it is not as straightforward
to draw indifference
curves as we did before.
So first, let's understand what
exactly this function means.
This function can be written
in an even simpler way.
This function can be written as this.
Utility equals x1
if x1 is indeed the minimum
between the two, x1 and x2, okay?
And utility equals x2
if x2 is now the minimum between the two.
Of course, the case in
which they're equal,
and in this case, since this
is a continuous function,
we can just give it to either of them
and we're gonna give it to the first one.
So this is what is going
on in this function.
Now, with this,
we need to see whether...
We need to see whether we can
draw an indifference curve
with this information.
And to that, let's note
that in the figure,
oops, let's just this white one.
Okay, so to draw this, we
can notice that things depend
on whether x1 is smaller or x2 is smaller.
So interestingly, we can
divide the space x1 and x2.
We can divide it exactly
in those two regions.
There's a region in
which x, let's do this.
Okay, there's a region in which
x1 is higher than x2
and there is a region in which x1
is smaller than or equal than x2.
So we have these two regions.
Now, if x1 is smaller than x2,
then only x1, notice, determines utility.
That means x2 does not
do anything for utility.
Therefore, indifference
curve must be vertical.
Why is that?
It's because changes.
Oops, but sorry.
Changes for higher or lower x2
in this region won't matter.
X1 is the only thing determining utility.
For that reason, indifference
curves will look like this.
Vertical with further
away indifference curves
having higher utility.
By the same token in the other region,
when x1 is above x2,
then x2 is gonna be the only
thing determining utility,
and therefore,
and therefore the indifference
curves will be flat.
Okay, so in this particular case,
this would be the indifference
curve for utility level one,
and this would be the indifference curve
for utility level three.
How do I know that?
Well, look at this.
Look at these points here.
Suppose this is one,
and let's talk about three points,
this point, this point and this point.
So let's call these
three points A, B, and C.
So what is point A?
Well, point A is the bundle,
one unit of x1, two units of x2.
The minimum between one and two
equals one.
B is the point that has one, one.
So one here, one here.
And the minimum, sorry,
between one and one is,
of course, one.
So same utility, which is expected
because we are claiming those three
are on the same indifference curve.
Finally, point C has this bundle.
Sorry, point C corresponds
to the bundle two, one.
And again, or similarly,
the bundle will be...
The utility will be the minimum
between two and one, which,
of course, is once again one.
So indeed, these three points belong
to the same indifference curve.
You could do the same
thing with a point like D.
A point like D is the bundle
or corresponds to the bundle three, three.
And this bundle three, three is such that
or has a utility of three,
of the minimum between three
and three, which is also three.
So the utility level is indeed
three for points like this
but it's also the same for a point like F.
In point F, we have bundle seven, three
and the minimum between seven and three,
it is still three and that
is why it still belongs
to this indifference curve
of utility level three.
Okay, I hope this clarifies
and now we can move on to
our next special preference.
Our next special preference
is a utility function
that we call Cobb-Douglas.
Cobb-Douglas generally takes this form.
It's the multiplication
of x1 power to A times x2 power to B
where both A and B are positive.
So here are three examples of Cobb-Douglas
because there are many, many functions
that can be Cobb-Douglas preferences
as they were many, many functions
that could be perfect complements
or many, many functions
that could be perfect substitutes.
There are also many functions,
even maybe more functions
that can be Cobb-Douglas.
So one of them could be where alpha and...
Sorry, where A and B are both 1/2
and which is x1 power to
1/2 times x2 power to 1/2.
Another one could be x1 times x2 cubed.
And in this case, that means
that A equals to one
and B equals to three.
Another one could be
this, x1 squared times X2
power to 0.75, which is A, two
or which is what would
happen of Cobb-Douglas
with A equals two and B equals 0.75.
This is a typical indifference map
of a Cobb-Douglas function.
Notice that it's not L-shaped
as it was for perfect complements.
It is not downward-sloping linear
as it was for perfect substitutes.
It's now convex and curvy in this manner.
So this is a typical indifference map
for Cobb-Douglas preferences.
(upbeat music)